Howard Giles Papers
Howard Giles Papers
1878-1958
Giles, Howard, 1876-1955.
2.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, lithographer. Correspondence, 1918-1957; exhibition catalogs, photographs, published material by and about Giles; and sketches and watercolors by Giles.
149001
Biographical History
Howard Giles (1876-1955) was an American painter, illustrator, and teacher. Born in Brooklyn, New York, he studied at the Art Students' League and with Jay Hambidge, whose theory of "dynamic symmetry" influenced Giles' work. In 1912 he began teaching at the New York School of Fine and Applied Art, and later was appointed Dean of the Art Department at the Nicholas Roerich Museum in New York, retiring as Dean Emeritus. Giles is represented in the permanent collections of major museums and in private collections.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Howard Giles Papers include biographical material, correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, published material, sketches, and watercolors.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing. Subject files includes manuscripts, medals, photographs, and published material. Manuscripts includes manuscripts about Mr. Giles, essays, letters on art, notes, manuscripts of others, sketches, watercolors of Giles' work, and a portfolio of students' work. Published material includes magazine articles, books, illustrations, newspaper clippings, and reproductions.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author, outgoing chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type.
Related Material
has made a concerted effort over the years to ensure that its manuscript and rare books holdings complement each other. As a result, many of our manuscript collections are supported by books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection. Please be sure to search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Blashfield, Edwin Howland, 1848-1936.; Giles, Howard, 1876-1955.; Gropper, William, 1897-1997.; Hambidge, Jay, 1867-1924.; Hampden, Walter, 1879-1955.; Henri, Robert, 1965-1929.; Phillips, W. S. (Walter Shelley), 1867-1940.; Roerich, Nicholas, 1874-1947.; Ross, Denman Waldo, 1853-1935.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Lithographers -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Paintings (visual works); Photographs.; Artists.; Lithographers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Sketches, undated (Box 1)
  - Watercolor studies, undated; 24 items (Box 1)
  - Watercolors, 1936; undated; 30 items (Box 1)
  - Watercolors (oversize), 1927-1930; 1932-1933,; 1937; 60 pieces (Oversize 1)
  - By others, 1921; 1930-1932,; 1936 (Box 1)
  - Portfolio of students' work in leather portfolio, 1934; 28 items (Oversize 2)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A-B, 1921-1923 (Box 1)
    - Art Institute of Chicago, 1918; 1921,; 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - Artists' Galleries, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Blashfield, Edwin Howland, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Brooklyn Museum, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1921-1924 (Box 1)
    - City Art Museum, 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - Cleveland Art Museum, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1923 (Box 1)
    - D-H, 1927; 1929,; undated (Box 1)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1923-1924; 1929 (Box 1)
    - Fine Arts Gallery of San Diego, 1926; 1927 (Box 1)
    - Fogg Art Museum (Harvard Univ.), 1927; 1929 (Box 1)
    - Gropper, William, circa 1920 (Box 1)
    - Hambidge, Jay, 1920-1923 (Box 1)
    - Hampden, Walter, undated (Box 1)
    - Henri, Robert, 1921; 1924 (Box 1)
    - K-R, 1924; 1928-1929,; 1936,; 1938 (Box 1)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Nat'l Academy of Design, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Phillips, W.S., undated (Box 1)
    - Ramsey, C.F., 1922 (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller, Abby, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Roerich, Nicholas, 1929; 1931,; 1934 (Box 1)
    - Ross, Denman W., 1923; 1925,; 1927,; 1929-1930 (Box 1)
    - S-Y, Unidentifiable, 1920; 1921,; 1925-1926,; 1929,; 1936 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - General, 1923-1925; 1927,; 1935,; undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Giles, Mrs. Howard (wife), 1955; 1957 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Awards, 1923; 1926,; 1935 (Box 1)
  - Bessemer, Auriel, undated (Box 1)
  - Carter, Evelyn, 1925; 1938,; 1941,; 1957 (Box 1)
  - Color charts, 1925; 1928 (Box 1)
  - Da Vinci, Leonardo, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Exhibitions, 1897; 1914,; 1923,; 1925,; 1929,; 1933,; 1936-1938,; 1957 (Box 2)
  - Hambidge, Jay and Dynamic Symmetry, 1919; 1923-1924,; 1929 (Box 2)
  - Medals, 1918; 1921,; 1926,; 1932-1933; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership Certificate, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Self and Family, 1933; undated (Oversize 2)
    - Travel, 1916; undated (Box 2)
    - Works, 1926; 1932,; 1945 (Oversize 2)
  - Programs, 1958; undated (Box 2)
  - Quotations from others
    - Ross, Denman W., 1929 (Box 2)
    - Various Authors, 1925; 1947 (Box 2)
- Manuscripts
  - About Giles by others, 1933; 1935,; 1958,; undated (Box 2)
  - Essays by Giles, 1921; undated (Box 2)
  - Letters on art, 1951; undated (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1950; undated (Box 3)
- Published material
  - Articles
    - About Giles, 1929-1931; 1936,; 1945,; undated (Box 4)
    - By Giles, 1921; 1930-1931 (Box 4)
    - By and about others, 1920; 1930-1933,; 1935-1936 (Box 4)
  - Books
    - The Salmagundi Club by W. H. Shelton, with 1 illustration by Giles, 1918; See for this item.
    - Sketching from Nature, T. Rowbitham, 1878; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please see to locate this item.
  - Magazine illustrations by Giles
    - Scribner's, August, 1913 (Box 4)
    - Scribner's, November, 1913 (Box 4)
    - Scribner's, December, 1913 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - About Giles, 1922-1924; 1926,; 1929,; 1932,; 1936-1937,; undated (Box 4)
    - By Giles, 1921; undated (Box 4)
    - By and about others, 1923; 1925,; 1928,; 1931-1932,; 1935-1936,; 1947 (Box 4)
  - Reproductions
    - Works by Giles, 1923; 1937; includes issue of Everyday Art, vol. 1 no. 5 (Box 4)
    - Works of others, undated (Box 4)